Guide to the Central Washington University Faculty Papers, Alice Yee 1968-2009
Central Washington University Archives and Special Collections
Central Washington University Faculty Papers, Alice Yee
1968-2009
Central Washington University, Archives and Special Collections 400 E University Way Ellensburg, WA 98926 (509) 963-1717 http://www.lib.cwu.edu/Archives-Special-Collections archive@cwu.edu
FP-0034
Yee, Alice
1 linear foot
Spanning the years 1968 to 2009, the Alice Yee Collection documents the work of Alice Yee, women's rights activist and former Dean of Women at Central Washington University.
Biographical Note
Alice Low Yee came of age in 1930s-1940s Spokane, WA. Yee earned a master’s degree and began teaching at Wenatchee Valley College. In 1960, she assumed a position as Dean of Women at Central Washington College of Education. In that position, she challenged restrictive curfews and dress codes for women. She remained at Central until 1966, then took a position as Dean of Women Students at Grinnell College in Iowa. There she encountered the quintessential ambience of the ‘60s—drugs, anti-war protests, and agitation for civil rights. In 1970, she returned to Central and soon married Robert Yee. In 1972, she established the university’s first Women’s Center, which aimed to support women at the university and in the wider community. Over the next few years, Yee built up the center, raising funds for educational outreach and special projects and establishing contacts with women’s organizations across the state.
In July of 1977, Central witnessed a key moment in the modern feminist movement, as the Washington State Conference on the Status of Women met in Ellensburg to elect 24 delegates to the National Women’s Conference, to be held that November in Houston, TX, in observance of International Women's Year (IWY). Two thousand church women, including a significant population of Mormon women, surprised local organizers in Ellensburg by showing up without pre-registering. As a result, the 4280 attendees often disagreed as they attended the conference’s 80 workshops. Feminists and fundamentalists were unable to reach consensus about the controversial women's issues of the day, including the Equal Rights Amendment, affirmative action, and gay and lesbian rights. This cleavage occurred in most International Women’s Year conferences, all of which enacted the nationwide debate about the necessity of reforms in women’s rights. Despite the inability of the delegates to reach agreement on key issues, 23 of the 24 delegates elected by the conference were strong proponents of the rights of women. Later that year, they represented Washington state at the national conference in Houston and together with delegates from across the nation, effectively agreed upon a final plan of action, which was presented to President Jimmy Carter.
Over the course of her career, Yee was involved not only in International Women’s Year but also in the League of Women Voters, the National Organization for Women (NOW), and Planned Parenthood. She served as member of the Ellensburg IWY Coordinating Committee, Vice Chair of the Ellensburg City Planning Commission, and member of the board for the Washington State League of Women Voters.
This collection consists of brochures, memos, reports, newspaper clippings, and meeting agendas collected by Alice Yee from 1968 to 2009 in her capacity as Dean of Women and founder of the Women’s Center at Central Washington University. These materials relate to the celebration of International Women’s Year in 1977, and the associated Washington State Conference for Women held in Ellensburg, WA. Additionally, the collection accounts for the financial and legislative climate impacting the university in the 1970s-2000s. The last series in the collection includes pamphlets and marketing materials held by the Parents Council at the university, meant for the parents of Central students.
Arranged in three series: I. International Women’s Year; II. Student and Faculty Affairs, Central Washington University; III. Parents, Central Washington University. Within series, materials are organized chronologically.
Open to the public for educational research.
“Women's Center: Summary of Activities of the Women's Center at Central Washington University, 1975-1989.” Box 1. The Cultural Heritage and Museum Project (CHAMP), Miscellaneous Files. RG061-06-49. Central Washington University Archives and Special Collections.
“Women’s Center Scrapbook, 1976.” Box 2. The Cultural Heritage and Museum Project (CHAMP), Miscellaneous Files. RG061-06-49. Central Washington University Archives and Special Collections.
“Newspaper clippings & Press Releases; Washington State Conference for Women 1977.” Box 17. University Relations Office. RG 027-06-61. Central Washington University Archives and Special Collections.
“1977 Washington State Women’s Conference & Related Materials Digital Collection.” Central Washington University Archives and Special Collections, Digital Collections. http://digital.lib.cwu.edu/
“Ellensburg Oral History Project: Alice Yee Interview.” Washington Women’s History Consortium. Accessed 1 May 2012. http://www.washingtonwomenshistory.org/themes/womensrights/oHistProj/yee.aspx
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Yee, Alice
Ellensburg (Wash.)
Women's rights--United States--History--20th century; College administrators--United States; International Women's Year, 1975--United States; Central Washington University--History
Colleges and Universities; Women; Washington (State)
- International Women’s Year, I
  - National Commission on the Observance of International Women’s Year—“Chronology of the Women’s Movement in the U.S., 1961-1975" (Box-folder 1-1)
  - National Commission on the Observance of International Women’s Year—“The Legal Status of Homemakers in Washington", 1976 (Box-folder 1-2)
  - National Commission on the Observance of International Women’s Year—Manual, 1976 (Box-folder 1-3)
  - Good Housekeeping, “18 Women, 417 Men", circa 1977 (Box-folder 1-4)
  - Washington State Conference for Women—Recommendations, 1977 (Box-folder 1-5)
  - Washington State Conference for Women—Registration, 1977 (Box-folder 1-6)
  - Washington State Conference for Women—Report, 1977 (Box-folder 1-7)
  - Washington State Women’s Council—“History, Activities, and Accomplishments, 1971-1977" (Box-folder 1-8)
  - Delegates to the National Women’s Conference, 1977 (Box-folder 1-9)
  - National Women’s Conference—Bulletins, 1977 (Box-folder 1-10)
  - National Women’s Conference—Plenary Agenda, 1977 (Box-folder 1-11)
  - National Women’s Conference—Remarks by Rosalynn Carter, November 19, 1977 (Box-folder 1-12)
  - National Women’s Conference—“Woman: 1977, The Status of American Women" (Box-folder 1-13)
- Faculty and student affairs, Central Washington University, II
  - Lectures by visiting professor Max Savalle, 1968 (Box-folder 2-1)
  - Faculty recruitment and retention strategy, 1977-1982 (Box-folder 2-2)
  - Ivory Nelson presidency, 1978-1999 (Box-folder 2-3)
  - Women’s Studies programs in Washington state, 1981-1982 (Box-folder 2-4)
  - Reviews of university functions, 1990-2000 (Box-folder 2-5)
  - Washington state legislation, 1993-2005 (Box-folder 2-6)
  - “Women in Politics: The Washington Paradigm" conference, 1993 (Box-folder 2-7)
  - Campus reorganization, 1995-1997 (Box-folder 2-8)
  - Miscellaneous university news, 1995-2001 (Box-folder 2-9)
  - Campus safety, circa 1990s (Box-folder 2-10)
  - Personnel policy and procedure, 2001-2004 (Box-folder 2-11)
- Parents, Central Washington University, III
  - CWU Parents, Events, 1980-1992 (Box-folder 3-1)
  - CWU Parents’ Guides, 1986-1992 (Box-folder 3-2)
  - University of Iowa Parents Association, circa 1986 (Box-folder 3-3)
  - “Central Parents" newsletter, 1989-1993 (Box-folder 3-4)
  - CWU Parents brochures and calendars, circa 1990s-2009 (Box-folder 3-5)
  - CWU Parents Council records, circa 1992-2006 (Box-folder 3-6)